if I had a time machine then what you're
going to be learning in this video is
the exact study guide and lesson plan
that I would go back in time and give
myself at the beginning of my trading
career this lesson plan and this study
guide would have saved me thousands of
hours of scouring through YouTube videos
trying to learn how to trade on my own
this lesson plan is an organized
step-by-step process that I wish I would
have known at the beginning of my
trading career again to speed up my
process to becoming profitable and today
I'm going to be sharing that with you so
if that sounds good go click that like
button for me go ahead and subscribe if
you are new and I'll be right back to
share with you a 2024 Study Guide to
Becoming
[Music]
profitable welcome back let's go ahead
and get started what you're going to be
learning is an 8mon plan that takes you
through everything you're going to need
to know in a step by step way each and
every month learning something that
builds on top of the last month until
you get to a point of actually
profitable trading so let's go and get
started with month number one pretty
obvious here month number one is going
to be mastering the basics of the market
you're trading it's kind of crazy to me
how many people including myself start
out their trading career and don't
master the basics of Forex before they
open a live account and try to start
trading a strategy they do that before
they know how to calculate a position
size in order to risk a small amount of
their account they do that sometimes
before they really understand the buy
and sell orders on the trading platform
they're using I've done the same exact
thing especially at the beginning of my
trading career understanding the basics
is extremely important and obviously if
you already know the basics you can skip
this step but if there's any of these 13
things that you do not have a complete
understanding of then it's time to go
back to the drawing board and learn
whatever it is that you don't know
because if you don't it's going to set
you up for failure in the long run in
your trading so let me briefly go
through these I'm sure you guys can read
but let me go ahead and try to read
myself I'm slightly dle so it might be
difficult but number one you obviously
need to know what a currency pairer is
if you're going to be trading in Forex
you will need to know what a pip is
you'll need to know how to calculate the
value of a pip you'll need to know what
leverage and margin are this is a huge
one that I see beginners and struggling
traders that have been trading for up to
a year sometimes still don't have a
grasp on Leverage and margin and how
they work that is a problem that's
something you're going to need to study
and figure out before you continue
trading with real money next up we have
the different types of Brokers and how
they work there are Market maker Brokers
and ecn Brokers you need to know the
difference and how they work so you can
pick the broker that best fits your
needs you need to master a trading
platform I personally use trading view
you need to know what a long versus a
short trade is you need to know what
entry stops and targets are what the
types of orders in trading are limit
stop and Market orders you need know how
to place entry stops and Targets in your
specific brokerage account you need to
know the different position sizes in
Forex and how to calculate a position
size and you need to know what a spread
is and how that works before you ever
start trading live and these are things
that I think you can Master within one
month pretty easily you should be able
to get through this within a couple of
weeks if you have a decent amount of
time to spend learning how to trade but
I'm thinking of someone with a 9 to-5
job that only has a couple hours a day
it may take up to about a month to learn
all of these different things now I've
have also put this where you can just
type in each of these into YouTube or
Google and it will give you the lessons
you need for instance if you type in
Google what is a currency pair that'll
give you what a currency pair is so on
and so forth so you can essentially just
type in what I have here and that could
be how you study each of these and I'm
confident that you can Master this like
I said within one month so month number
one down you have to master the basics
let's move on now what would I study in
month number two if I wasn't profitable
yet in 2024 month number two is when
things actually get fun after mastering
the basics you're now going to master
charts you're going to master the
ability to read a price chart and that
all starts with number one on this list
which is understanding the anatomy of a
Candlestick after that you're going to
need to understand how to read an entire
Candlestick chart based on a lot of
different candlesticks after that you're
going to need to learn how to identify a
trending market then you'll need to
learn how to identify important
structure levels after that we're
talking about Candlestick patterns my
favorites are the engulfing and Hammer
SL upside down Hammer shooting star
whatever you want to call it those are
my two favorite Candlestick patterns
chart patterns are the next step on this
list my favorite chart patterns are by
far double bottoms and double tops
followed closely by Head and Shoulder
and inverse Head and Shoulder patterns
next up we have breakout patterns like
flag patterns and just consolidation
breakouts in general and after that of
course you can learn about indicators if
you choose to use them now in terms of
just strictly price action 1 through
7even is all you'll need to study if
you're just going to be a strictly price
action Trader but if you want to
incorporate indicators into some of the
Strate iies that you're going to be
using or building later on then you'll
want to learn about indicators as well
my favorite indicators are the RSI EMAs
like the 50p EMA which is my favorite
EMA to use and the ATR indicator which
gives you the average of the last 14
candles so those may be some indicators
you want to study now again I've laid
this out in a way where you can
literally just type this into a Google
or YouTube search in order to learn
about any of this a lot of you may
already know the anatomy of a
Candlestick how to read a chart things
like that again skip any of this that
you already know but if there are things
on this list that you don't know yet
then go back and study it because this
Mastery level understanding of
candlesticks chart patterns breakout
patterns is going to be the foundation
of trading strategies that you're going
to have to build or learn in order to
ever be profitable so you want a solid
foundation you want to understand all of
this like the back of your hand you have
to know all of these things in order to
ever combine them into a trading
strategy so that's why it's important
that you master these things now now so
again month number two this is what I
would master in order to put myself on
the path to profitable trading by the
end of 2024 in month number three I
would spend my time developing or
learning a profitable trading strategy
now learning a profitable trading
strategy is very obvious you just go
online you search profitable trading
strategies you find one that fits your
personality you test it in historic data
and see if it is in fact profitable
that's pretty easy let's talk about
developing a profitable trading strategy
though so in terms of develop veloping a
profitable trading strategy all we're
going to be doing is taking all the
technical factors that we talked about
in month two and we're going to combine
a specific number of those in order to
create a strategy I think it'll be
easiest for me just to do this with you
very briefly here on the chart so as you
can see next here I have C this is how I
create strategies in order to make sure
that they are rules-based enough for me
to follow at first I have conditions
that that I have to see before I look
for an entry reason conditions could be
things like the trend of the market is
up or down the market is at a major
level of structure the RSI indicator is
overbought with Divergence oversold with
Divergence all of those would be
examples of conditions so I have
specific conditions I must see before I
even look for an entry reason and I have
to have rules for those conditions so a
strategy is essentially just the rules
that we follow before we can actually
execute a trade and a strategy is
extremely important so that we stay
consistent we don't swap the way we're
trading constantly because doing that is
a recipe for disaster you need a trading
strategy in order to be profitable so
this is the way we're going to build one
conditions first then we're going to
look for identifiable entries that are
rules based after that we need rules for
our stop-loss and rules for our Target I
call this C and I'm going to go ahead
and show you this kind of inaction on on
the chart now so one of my favorite
strategies to trade is something I call
the otz system which stands for optimal
trading zones system the way this works
and it's an actual rules-based strategy
that I developed is I look for prices to
be in a specific Trend will go downtrend
on this one so condition number one
would be Market in a downtrend I then
look for a major level of structure that
market pulls back to so here we have
Market a downtrend making new lower lows
also making new lower highs we're in a
downtrend we have a major level of
structure right here that I identify as
the previous level of support that was
broken and it also has been tested
multiple times so that's condition
number two is I need that level to be
there after seeing that I want to see a
chart pattern occur right here at this
level so as you can see we're just
combining everything I talked about in
month number two which is we're
combining trend wind with a major level
of structure and now a chart pattern
which would be a double top in this case
all of those would fall under conditions
for this strategy what's after
conditions I want to look for an entry
reason an entry reason for me is going
to be a Candlestick pattern after the
double top so for instance if I got the
double top and then we see a shooting
star candle or an upside down Hammer
right there at the end of that double
top that would be an entry reason what I
mean by entry is that Candlestick would
be the real reason that I pressed the
sell button in this case going short
then I have to have a rule for my stop
loss in order to have a complete
strategy I need to know where I'm
getting out if I'm wrong about a trade
so my stop loss would go above the
highest high of that double top and I
need to have a rule for my target that's
what the T stands for so the rule for
the Target may be something like at the
previous swing low is where I'm placing
my target so this is what that trade
setup would look like and this would be
the full strategy and all of the rules
based on conditions entries stops and
targets and in month number three this
is what I would do I would develop or
learn a profitable trading system
because that is something that's going
to be pivotal in your success as a
Trader now we have plenty of trading
strategies available here on the channel
feel free to look through any of them
that you would like to and also don't be
scared to try to develop your own
strategy just by combining a number of
conditions along with a specific entry
reason specific rules for stops and
specific rules from targets all based on
what you learn about in month number two
so that would be my plan for month
number three now on to month number four
this is the month where you need to be
really careful if you live with a spouse
make sure they understand that you are
going to be moody you are going to have
headaches because the back testing
process is one of the most frustrating
things I think I've ever done in my life
but it is absolutely necessary and
before I get too far ahead of myself let
me explain what back testing is for you
back testing is going to be the process
of taking the rules-based strategy that
you have either developed or learned
from someone else going through historic
data on a chart on a specific currency
pair and a specific time frame and
documenting every time those rules were
met every time you would have had a
trade based on that strategy throughout
at least the last 100 instances that it
happened that is the process of back
testing now why do we do this
well for one thing we want to make sure
that the strategy we're trading has been
profitable over at least the last 100
trades because that tells us that it's
likely to continue being profitable
another reason we do this and probably
the biggest reason is because during
this back testing process back testing
is one of the largest levers we have for
our trading psychology to improve our
mindset our trading psychology and our
discipline and the reason for that is
during the back testing process you're
going to see the rules-based strategy
you've created or learn earned go
through draw downs and go through losing
streaks but hopefully come out the other
side profitable and seeing that
firsthand through the back testing
process will make it easier when you're
trading live and you have inevitable
losses every trading strategy will come
with some losses every trading strategy
will have draw downs and you need to be
prepared to deal with those when you're
live trading back testing and seeing it
happen in the past is one of the best
ways to prepare yourself for those draw
Downs in the future when you are in fact
trading with real money now on the
channel we have a full tutorial that
talks about how to back test and shows
you a full tutorial on how to do it
properly feel free to check that out
this video is more of a study guide so I
don't have time to explain exactly how
to back test throughout this video but
again we have videos on the channel that
will teach you how to do everything that
we have talked about so far up to month
4 and everything we're going to talk
about later in this video so treat this
video again like a study guide and go
back to all of these and look at them as
lessons that you have to learn before
you're going to be able to be a
profitable Trader but the back testing
process after you learn how to do it
through that video or any other video
you watch on back testing is going to be
something you have to do yourself
because again you need to see the
strategy go through draw down and come
out profitable you need to see the
strategy have losing streaks but still
be profitable at the end of 100 Trade
sample size to improve your own trading
psychology now once you've back tested
multiple currency pairs that's when
you're going to step into the process of
optimizing your trading strategy now
what does this mean different currency
pairs are going to have different
personalities what that means is that
you may have a trend continuation
strategy and there's certain currency
pairs that Trend really well a lot of
the Yen pairs tend to Trend really well
so what will happen is if you try to
trade a trend continuation strategy on a
currency pairer that's notorious for
being a consolidating pairer then that
strategy is not going to perform as well
on that consolidating pair so when we're
optimizing what we're doing is picking
out the best currency pairs for the
specific strategy that we're trading to
give ourselves the best odds of being
profitable with that specific strategy
and another thing you may want to
optimize for is what times does the
strategy perform the best are there
certain times that it doesn't perform
well so what you're going to do in your
back testing process is document when
you're placing that trade and if that
trade won or lost what was your reward
to risk ratio on that specific trade and
out of a 100 Trade sample size did that
make money on a specific currency pair
and then you're going to pick the top
performing currency pairs after you've
back tested a handful of pairs and
that's the optimization process that you
will need to do after back testing so
month number four if I was not quite
profitable and I took the correct steps
month one through three I had the basics
down I knew how to read a chart I
understood everything I needed to know
about Candlestick charts and indicators
I developed a trading strategy in month
number four I would spend the entire
month back testing and optimizing the
trading strategy that I developed in
month number three month number five for
me would be all about risk management
now risk management is self-explanatory
it's literally you managing risk inside
of your trading account but I have a
very specific way that I do this that
I'm going to explain in just a second
and we also have very detailed videos
diving into risk management here on the
channel feel free to check those out but
risk management to me is broken down
into three different categories first
off we have what is called risk Capital
now risk Capital refers to the amount of
money you start your trading account
with and by the way there are no right
or wrong answers to any of these
everything about your risk management
plan needs to be personalized for you
every person on the planet has varying
risk tolerance which means you may have
a very high risk tolerance and you may
want to put most of your life savings
into a trading account whereas someone
down the street doesn't have that kind
of risk tolerance and they only want to
put a very small portion of their net
worth at risk in a speculative trading
account like a Forex account so risk
capital is the first stage of a good
risk management plan and that's going to
be the amount of money you actually put
at risk in a trading account when you're
doing something as risky as Forex
Trading next up we have risk per trade
this simply means how much money are you
willing to risk on each trade you place
for every trade that you place you need
to have an area even a stop loss order
for me at least that's what I use but
you need at least an area where you know
I'm wrong about this trade and I'm going
to get out and accept my loss accepting
that loss means you're going to lose a
specific amount of your account risk per
trade means what am I willing to lose on
a trade for me this number is between 1
and 3% there is no wrong answer here you
could be very risk tolerant and go I
don't mind losing 10% per trade you
could you could be very risk averse and
go I don't want to lose more than half a
percent whenever I'm risking money on a
specific trade but if I was a complete
beginner and did not have all my ducks
in a row in terms of knowing exactly how
to trade then I would be risking a very
small amount of my account value on
every trade because obviously if you're
risking 10% of your account per trade
that you place and you don't know how to
trade yet you are very likely to blow
your account now the third part of a
good risk management plan is over
exposure and this just means how many
trades are you willing to be in at once
I'll give you an example of this to make
it easy personally I can only be in five
trades at once at a 2% risk the reason
for this is if I lose all five of those
trades because of some crazy news event
where the markets are going nuts then at
that point I'm going to be losing 10% in
a in like a flash in the snap of a
finger that's tough but it's something
I'm willing to deal with and that is my
overall exposure rule is that I can be
in five trades at once or in other words
I can have 10% of my account value at
risk at any one given time so overall
exposure is just how many trades can I
be in at a specific risk and these are
the three things that in month number
five I would take and consider after
again feel free to watch a couple of the
more detailed risk management videos
that we have here on the channel feel
free to study risk management throughout
month 5 as well but after studying it
and really comprehending it above what
I've just told you that's really brief
version after you actually comprehend it
it's important to sit down and think and
consider very carefully what you want
for your risk capital for your risk per
trade and for your overall exposure what
are numbers in all three of those that
will keep you out of your emotions when
you're trading to give you another brief
lesson obviously if you're risking 10%
on a trade you are going to be highly
emotional if that trade starts going
south if it doesn't go your direction
whereas if you're risk rking 1% or less
you're going to be a lot less emotional
on that trade so risk management is
going to be a lever we use again to
manage our emotions keep our mindset
right to help with our trading
psychology and our discipline so make
sure the numbers you choose keep you in
a good emotional state while you're
trading so month number five is Master
risk management and develop a risk
management plan that's exactly what I
would do in month number five if I could
go back in time and give myself this
study guide at the beginning of my
trading career care in month number six
I would focus entirely on mastering
trading psychology if you allow emotions
to make your trading decisions for you
emotions like fear and greed to be the
reason why you're making decisions while
you're trading with live money then it
is almost inevitable that you will blow
your account so being able to manage
those emotions is extremely important
and that's why it's so important to
master trading psychology now for me one
of the biggest influences on my own
trading psychology and one of the people
I watched read and listened to the most
when trying to master my trading
Psychology was a guy named Mark Douglas
so I would suggest in month number six
that you go back and start reading
watching listening to everything you can
by Mark Douglas when you do if you've
ever seen any of our videos on trading
psychology you will see a lot of
parallels we see trading psychology in a
very similar way so that would be the
first step in mastering trading
psychology in month number six now we
have some things that we can use as
levers to improve our Trading psychology
and to keep emotions out of our trading
these things are using proper risk
management now although risk management
isn't trading psychology they are
parallels they go together and the
reason they go together is because the
more you are risking of your hard-earned
money the more emotional you're going to
be and the harder time you're going to
have controlling your emotions while
you're trading so using proper risk
management is one of the levers we have
to improve our trading psychology number
two it's going to be to back test your
trading strategy as we've already talked
talked about back testing you'll see
your strategy go in and out of draw
Downs you'll see your strategy have
losing streaks but then come out the
other side profitable and that will
improve your trading psychology it will
help you when the time comes and you're
live trading and you see a strategy
start to go through a draw down when
you're live trading and you see two
three losses in a row you can look back
at your back tested data and you can
tell yourself oh yeah this is perfectly
normal it's exactly what happened
throughout my back testing the next
thing is to have proper expectations
trading is not a get-rich quick scheme
no matter how many marketers try to tell
you it is it's going to be something
that takes you a fair amount of time to
master and then you'll have to save up
money or work with a prop firm in order
to have the capital to really start
affecting your livelihood to really get
to a point where you can quit your day
job that's the process you're going to
have to do and that's going to take
longer than most beginners think so keep
that in mind and try to have proper
expectations around your trading number
four is demo trade the exact strategy
that you plan to trade live I see a lot
of beginners making this mistake they
will jump into a demo account before
they created a strategy before they have
any rules they don't have a trading plan
they just create a demo account jump in
and start trading that does not help you
at all other than helping you figure out
the buttons to click in order to buy and
sell on your trading platform it really
doesn't do anything for you to demo
trade that style now what does help is
demo trading a strategy you've created
that you've already back tested you
using a risk management plan you've
already created if you do exactly what
you're going to do when you start
trading live in a demo account that's
something that can really improve your
trading psychology as well because again
kind of like back testing you're getting
to see the strategy that you're going to
be trading live go in and out of draw
downs and stuff like that but you're not
having to risk real money yet because
you're doing it in a demo account and
what that's going to do just like with
back testing is when in live trading
that scenario happens and you lose a
couple of trades in a row you you have
already seen it in your demo trading
you've already seen it in your back
testing so your emotional state doesn't
get affected nearly as much as it would
if you didn't take these steps if you
didn't back test and you didn't demo
trade so month number six would be all
about trading psychology for me if I was
starting over as a brand new Trader now
let's move on to month number seven so
in month number seven if you followed
all the other instructions correctly
through the previous months you will
have a full trading strategy or multiple
trading strategies that are rules based
that you've already back tested and seem
to be profitable in historic data and
you will have a full risk management
plan that you think will keep you out of
your emotions based on your own risk
tolerance month number seven is going to
be one of the easiest months you have
and it honestly should not take you
anywhere near a month but essentially
all you're going to do in order to
create what we call a trading plan is
write out the strategies you're going to
be using along with all the rules and
write out your actual risk management
plan now this trading plan is exactly
what it sounds like it's something that
you're going to take and read every
morning and this is the plan you have
for every single day that you trade this
will keep you from switching strategies
keep you from Trading based on emotions
or trading out of greed just because you
want to make money that day instead
you'll have a written plan that you have
to follow every single day and the
beauty of this is it's a plan that's
already proven to be profitable through
your back testing process and writing
this down and having it beside your desk
whether you write it down or put it in a
Google doc whatever you choose to do is
something that will be extremely helpful
as you begin to live trade so simple
enough month number seven is write down
all the rules you've already created
create your full trading plan now in
month number eight if I was not
profitable yet and I'd followed the
steps all the way up to this point this
is when I would start a demot trading
account and this is when I would start
demo trading the exact trading plan that
I created in month number seven now this
demo trading process is meant to one
ensure that you can actually exploit
your strategy with with all of your
prior obligations you may have to sleep
we all do so that's going to be
something that gets in the way whereas
when you were back testing it didn't get
in the way you may have obligations like
children or obligations like a full-time
job that you didn't account for in your
back testing so this demo trading is
going to be you actually placing trades
using your full strategy to make sure
you can do it even with all of your
other prior obligations now this demo
trading process also is meant to improve
your trading psychology as we've already
talked about and so for that reason I'll
always suggest to demo trade anywhere
between 1 and 3 months if you can get to
that thre month Mark you normally get to
see your strategy go in and out of a
draw down within a 3-month period within
a 90day period so that's what you're
really looking for in this demo trading
process is you want to see your strategy
go through a draw down and then come
back by the end of 90 days profitable
obviously you can choose how long you
want to demo trade if you want to demo
trade longer that's completely fine if
you want to do a little bit shorter
that's completely up to you but just
make sure that you are completely
comfortable with all the risks involved
in trading and that you're completely
comfortable with the trading platform
you're using to place trades and that
you're completely comfortable with all
the rules you've created for your full
trading Plan before you decide to trade
with real money and again I'm going to
stress this whenever you're doing this
demo trading I know it's not real money
but it is extremely important that you
follow the exact rules you've set forth
for your full trading plan when you're
going through this process for 1 to 3
months or longer depending on what you
would like to do and after this demo
trading process congratulations you're
ready to trade live of course whenever
you feel comfortable let's do a final
recap on your 2024 Study Guide to
Becoming a profitable Trader month
number one you're going to master the
basics month number two you're going to
master Candlestick charts month number
three you're going to develop or learn a
trading strategy month number four
you're going to back test and optimize
that strategy and in month number five
you're going to develop your own risk
management plan based on your risk
tolerance month number six you're going
to master trading Psychology by reading
watching and listening to everything you
can find from Mark Douglas along with
implementing the levers that we have
that we can use to improve our own
trading psychology like Risk Management
back testing and demo trading in month
number seven you're going to take all
the rules that you've created for your
strategy or strategies that you plan to
trade for your risk management plan
you're just going to write them down in
what we call a full trading plan and in
month number eight you're going to start
your demo testing process with this full
trading plan so that you can see it go
in and out of draw down and get
accustomed to trading your strategies
using your risk management plan in a
live market scenario now obviously you
can feel free to go just Google or
YouTube search all of these lessons that
I've shared throughout this video using
this entire study guide as a lesson plan
to becoming profitable in 2024 but we
also have some space available in the
TDC forx University where we go through
each and every one of these in order in
a very organized University style course
and along with that you'll get guidance
from me personally this is a mentorship
program you can ask me any questions
that you have and it'll be me personally
getting back to you on top of that we
also send out three to five email alerts
per week of Trades I'm actually placing
based on the strategies you're learning
in the course and you'll get access to
the protrader report which is a report I
send out every Monday talking about the
levels of structure I'm paying attention
to for possible trades and the trades
I'm looking to take coming up in the
week ahead so if that sounds interesting
to you go ahead and click the top Link
in the description or go to www. TTC FX
university.com to find out all the
details on the TTC forx University if
not that's completely fine too just make
sure you go and click that like button
for me if you made it all the way to the
end subscribe if you are new comment
that you made it to the end and I'll try
to like every comment that made it this
far I know this video probably wasn't as
exciting as watching me trade or
watching me analyze a chart but this was
a literal study guide and lesson plan to
do exactly what I would do if I could go
back in time and lay myself out a plan
to become profitable within a year this
is what I would tell myself this is what
I would have taken back in time using
the DeLorean and giv myself back in 2013
so with that said I wish you all the
best of luck in your trading I hope you
enjoyed this video and I'll talk to you
in the next one see you soon